A Finding Aid to the Exhibition Records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art, 1943-1975, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Exhibition records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art
1943-1975
bulk 1964-1975
Archives of American Art
Finch College. Museum of Art
Varian, Elayne H.
AAA.finccoll
Archival Resource Key
20.9 Linear feet
The exhibition records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art measure 20.9 linear feet and date from 1943 to 1975, with the bulk of records dating from the period its galleries were in operation, from 1964 to 1975. Over two-thirds of the collection consists of exhibition files, which contain a wide range of documentation including artist files, checklists, correspondence, writings, photographs, interviews, numerous films and videos, artist statements, printed materials, and other records. Also found within the collection are administrative records of the museum, artist files, and papers of the Contemporary Wing's director and curator, Elayne Varian, which were produced outside of her work at Finch College.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical / Historical
The Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art, later called simply the "Contemporary Wing," was established in 1964 by the president of Finch College, Roland De Marco, as an extension the Finch College Museum of Art in New York City.
Its mission was to educate art history students at the Manhattan women's college who were interested in working with contemporary art. DeMarco, himself an art collector, hired Elayne Varian as director and curator of the contemporary wing. DeMarco met Varian in the New York office of the prominent international art dealership Duveen Brothers, where she had worked since the mid-1940s, most recently as an art dealer. Varian received her art education in Chicago, where she studied art history and education at the University of Chicago, and took classes in film at the Bauhaus and in fine art the Art Institute of Chicago. Sensitive to emerging art movements in galleries and studios around the city of New York, as the contemporary wing's curator, Varian quickly established a reputation for thoughtfully conceived, cutting-edge exhibitions which were consistently well-received by the press.
Under Varian, the Contemporary Wing carried out a dual mission of showing work of living artists and educating students and the public about the artwork and museum work in general. Varian used the galleries to provide practical training to students interested in a gallery or museum career throughout its existence. For several years, she also maintained an assistantship position for post-graduate museum professionals to gain experience in the field, many of whom went on to careers in museums across New York State.
The Contemporary Wing's best-known exhibitions formed a series of six shows called Art in Process, held between 1965 and 1972. Each of the Art in Process shows took a different medium, including painting, sculpture, collage, conceptual art, installation art, and serial art, and brought the process of art-making into the gallery with the artworks in various ways. For example, for Art in Process V (1972), the show about installation art, the galleries were open to the public for the entire process of its installation, allowing visitors to watch the works take shape. Another show entitled Documentation (1968) exhibited artworks with documentation such as artist's notes, sales records, and conservation records, bringing to light the value of record-keeping in the visual arts. Two exhibitions entitled Projected Art were also innovative, with the first (1966-1967) bringing experimental films from the cinema to the galleries, and the second (1971) showing artists' processes via footage and slides of artists working. Another show, Artists' Videotape Performances (1971), involved both screening of and creation of works in the gallery using a range of experiments with recent video technology. The museum also participated in an experimental broadcast of an artwork entitled Talk Out! by Douglas Davis, in which a telephone in the gallery allowed visitors to participate in its creation while it was broadcast live from Syracuse, NY. Other exhibitions that showcased experimentation in art included N-Dimensional Space (1970), on holography in art, Destruction Art(1968), on destructive actions being incorporated into contemporary art-making, and Schemata 7 (1967), a show about the use of environments in contemporary art, whose working title was "Walk-in Sculpture."
Other popular exhibitions at the Contemporary Wing included shows on Art Deco (1970) and Art Nouveau (1969). Several shows mined the private collections of prominent contemporary art collectors including Martha Jackson, Betty Parsons, George Rickey, Paul Magriel, Jacques Kaplan, Josephine and Philip Bruno, and Carlo F. Bilotti. A number of exhibitions featured contemporary art from overseas including Art from Belgium (1965), Art from Finland (1973), Seven Swedish Painters (1965), and Art in Jewelry (1966), which featured mainly international jewelry artists. Retrospective exhibitions of Hans Richter, Hugo Weber, and James Brooks were also held.
Hundreds of contemporary artists were shown at the Contemporary Wing in the eleven years of its existence, including many who came to be leading figures in contemporary art, and some who already were, including Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Mel Bochner, Eva Hesse, Lynda Benglis, Bruce Nauman, Robert Morris, Lawrence Weiner, Robert Smithson, Sol Le Witt, Dan Flavin, Philip Pearlstein, and Yayoi Kusama, to name just a few.
The Contemporary Wing and the entire Finch College Museum of Art shut its doors in 1975, when Finch College closed due to lack of funds. The permanent collection was sold at that time, and the proceeds were used to pay Finch College employee salaries. Elayne Varian went on to the position of curator of contemporary art at the John and Mabel Ringling Museum in Sarasota, Florida. She died in 1987.
Scope and Contents
The exhibition records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art measure 20.9 linear feet and date from 1943 to 1975, with the bulk of records dating from the period its galleries were in operation, from 1964 to 1975. Over two-thirds of the collection consists of exhibition files, which contain a wide range of documentation including artist files, checklists, correspondence, writings, photographs, interviews, numerous films and videos, artist statements, printed materials, and other records. Also found within the collection are administrative records of the museum, artist files, and papers of the Contemporary Wing's director and curator, Elayne Varian, which were produced outside of her work at Finch College.
Administrative records include records relating to the general operation of the Contemporary Wing concerning fundraising, professional associations, budget, contact information for artists, donors, and lenders to exhibitions. Also found are records of the permanent collection of artworks acquired by the museum between 1964 and 1975 from contemporary artists and collectors of contemporary art.
Artist files contain basic biographical information on over 150 contemporary artists, with scattered correspondence, photographs, technical information about artworks, artist statements, and other writings. Artist files also include an incomplete run of artist questionnaires gathered by the New York Arts Calendar Annual for 1964.
Elayne Varian's personal papers include curatorial records, a course schedule and syllabus related to her teaching activities, and various writings. Curatorial projects documented in Varian's papers include three programs produced outside of Finch College, including a juried show at the New York State Fair in 1967, a film series at Everson Museum of Syracuse University, and an exhibition at Guild Hall in East Hampton in 1973. Several of Varian's writing projects involved interviews, which are also found in this series in the form of sound recordings and transcripts. Interview-based writing projects include individual profiles on Brian O'Doherty and Babette Newberger, and interviews conducted for an article on the artist-dealer relationship published in Art in America (January 1970). Dealers interviewed for the latter project include Leo Castelli, Virginia Dwan, John Gibson, Richard Feigen, Arnold Glimcher, Fred Mueller, Martha Jackson, Sidney Janis, Betty Parsons, Seth Siegelaub, and Howard Wise. Artists interviewed include Roy Lichtenstein, Adolph Gottlieb, and Charles Ross.
Exhibition files, comprising the bulk of the collection, document exhibitions held in the Contemporary Wing during its existence from 1964 to 1975. Types of records found in the series include exhibition catalogs, correspondence, loan agreements, lists, contact information, insurance valuations of artworks, photographs, biographical information on artists, clippings, posters, press releases, and other publicity materials. In addition to the rich textual and photographic records found for exhibitions, numerous audiovisual recordings are also found, some of which were made in preparation for an exhibition, some document mounted exhibitions, and others are artworks themselves or components of artworks exhibited in the galleries. Interviews with artists, dealers, and others involved in exhibitions include Alan Sonfist, Mel Bochner, Hans Richter, Ruth Richards, James Brooks and Janet Katz, Margaret Benyon, Irwin Hollander (transcript only), David Anderson, Doris Chase, Will Insley, Michael Kirby, Les Levine, Ursula Meyer, Brian O'Doherty, Charles Ross, Tony Smith, Douglas Davis, Jane Davis, Russ Connor, Les Levine, Michael Mazur, Paul Gedeohn, and physicists Lloyd G. Cross, Allyn Z. Lite, and Gerald Thomas Bern Pethick. Video artworks, recordings of performances, or components of multimedia artworks are found by artists Vito Acconci, Kathy Dillon, Douglas Davis, Dan Graham, Les Levine, Bruce Nauman, Michael Netter, Eric Siegel, and Robert Whitman. A film of the Art in Process: The Visual Development of a Structure (1966) exhibition is found, and video recordings of artists Lynda Benglis, Michael Singer, and Sam Wiener form as part of the documentation for the Projected Art: Artists at Work (1971) exhibition.
Existence and Location of Copies
All of the sound and video recordings in this collection, and two of the motion picture films, were digitized for research access in 2013 and are available at the Archives of American Art offices. The rest of the collection was digitized in 2018 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website. Materials which have not been digitized include blank pages, blank versos of photographs, and duplicates. In some cases, exhibition catalogs and other publications have had their covers, title pages, and relevant pages digitized.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Archives of American Art acquired these records from the Finch College Museum of Art after it closed permanently in June 1975.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with curator Elayne Varian conducted by Paul Cummings, May 2, 1975.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 4 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1950-1975 (2 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, 22, OV 23)
Series 2: Artist Files, 1958-1975 (2.4 linear feet; Boxes 3-4, 22, OV 23, FC 27-28)
Series 3: Elayne Varian Personal Papers, 1965-1970 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 5-6)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1943-1975 (14.9 linear feet; Boxes 6-22, OV 24-25, FC 26)
Transcripts; Art dealers -- New York (State) -- New York; Interviews; Photographs; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Video artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Museum records; Gallery directors; Museum administrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Gallery owners; Museum curators -- New York (State) -- New York; Acconci, Vito, 1940-; Glimcher, Arnold B.; Benglis, Lynda, 1941-; Anderson, David K., 1935-; Bochner, Mel, 1940-; Benyon, Margaret, 1940-; Janis, Sidney, 1896-1989; Castelli, Leo; Brooks, James, 1906-1992; Jackson, Martha Kellogg; Hollander, Irwin; Insley, Will, 1929-2011; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974; Graham, Dan, 1942-; Smith, Tony, 1912-1980; Siegelaub, Seth, 1941-; Richter, Hans, 1888-1976; Parsons, Betty; O'Doherty, Brian; Nauman, Bruce, 1941-; Kirby, Michael; Chase, Doris, 1923-; Cross, Lloyd G.; Davis, Douglas; Dwan, Virginia; Feigen, Richard L., 1930-; Wise, Howard; Weiner, Sam; Sonfist, Alan; Mazur, Michael, 1935-2009; Meyer, Ursula, 1915-; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997; Levine, Les, 1935-
- Administrative Records, 1950-1975; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 22, OV 23
  Arrangement
  Correspondence, photographs, research, and printed material related to specific exhibitions is found in Series 4, Exhibition Files. A number of the artists represented in the museum's permanent collection are also documented in Series 2, Artist Files.
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes records relating to the operations of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum, including correspondence, pamphlets, brochures, flyers, notes, clippings, contact information, records related to grant applications and grant projects, records relating to the museum's permanent collection, photographs, and research files on a variety of subjects. Also found is a radio interview from 1968 on one sound tape reel with the Director of the Contemporary Study Wing, Elayne Varian, about the mission of the gallery and its exhibition program.
  Permanent collection records include letters of acknowledgement to artists and other donors for donations of artworks spanning the life of the gallery, lists of acquisitions, and photographs of artworks, many of which are negatives. Note that the list of permanent collection artworks listed by artist only lists works acquired between 1964 and 1966.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Materials which have not been digitized include blank pages, blank versos of photographs, and duplicates. In some cases, exhibition catalogs and other publications have had their covers, title pages, and relevant pages digitzed.
  - Annual Report, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Associations, American Association of Museums, 1966, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in Box 22, folder 1.
  - Associations, Artist-Tenants Association, 1963-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Associations, Concerned Citizens for the Arts, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Associations, Friends of the Finch College Museum, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Associations, Gallery Association of New York State, 1972-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Associations, Gallery Association of New York State, 1972-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Associations, Gallery Association of New York State, 1972-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Associations, International Council of Museums, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Associations, New York City Department of Cultural Affairs, Artists Certification Committee, 1971-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Associations, New York City Museums Council, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Associations, Partnership for the Arts, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brochures, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Budget Notes, circa 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Contacts, Artists - A-J, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Contacts, Artists - K-R, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Contacts, Artists - S-Z, circa 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Contacts, Donors - A-L, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Contacts, Donors - M-Z, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Contacts, Lenders, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence - Undated, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Gifts, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Records relate to non-artwork gifts.
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Oversized Item in OV 23, folder 1.
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Insurance, circa 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Interview with Elayne Varian for the "Art in New York" Radio Series, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Interview conducted by Bernard Murphy, broadcast by WNYC in New York, NY.
  - Invitations, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lists of Artworks and Lenders to Exhibitions, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Museum Accreditation, 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Museum Membership, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Notes, circa 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Permanent Collection, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Acknowledgement Letters, Antonakos - Youngerman, 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Acknowledgement Letters, Antonakos - Youngerman, 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lists of Acquisitions by Year, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Lists of Acquisitions by Year, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Lists of Acquisitions by Year, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Lists of Acquisitions by Year, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Lists of Drawings and Paintings by Artist, circa 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Paintings out of Museum, circa 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Photographs of Artworks, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Photographs of Artworks, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Photographs of Artworks, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Photographs of Artworks, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Photographs of Artworks, circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Photographs of Exhibition Installation, circa 1965-circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Problems, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Artworks (Not in Permanent Collection), circa 1964-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Photographs of Unidentified People, circa 1965-circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Possible Future Exhibitions, 1966, 1969-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Possible Future Exhibitions, circa 1966-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Possible Future Exhibitions, circa 1966-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Possible Future Exhibitions, circa 1966-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Research Files, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Art Collections, 1964-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Art Collections, 1964-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Art Collections, 1964-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Art Collections, 1964-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Kasser Foundation, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Charles Gifford Dyer, 1950-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Contains correspondence detailing provenance and insurance valuation for Dyer's series of paintings of the Acropolis, then held by Wesleyan Library.
    - Conceptual Art, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Experiments in Art and Technology (E.A.T.), 1967-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Tamarind Lithography Workshop, circa 1961-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Sculpture Garden, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Shipping Receipts, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Tax Exempt Certification, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Oversized Administrative Records, American Association of Museums Certificate digitized with box 1, folder 2, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Administrative Records, Research Files, Experiments in Art and Technology (E.A.T.) digitized with box 2, folder 48, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 1)